Guide to the Stanford University, Committee of Fifteen, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Committee of Fifteen, records
1965-1972
SC0600
Stanford University. Committee of Fifteen.
1.5 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer
Information about Access
None.
Historical Note
The Committee of Fifteen, first constituted in the fall of 1965, is composed of six faculty, six students, and three staff representatives. It was directed by President Wallace Sterling in November 1965 to draft recommendations concerning judicial procedures and appellate review, although it also considered other issues pertaining to student affairs. After two years of study, the Committee proposed the Legislative and Judicial Charter, which was approved by a student referendum, the Academic Council, and the Board of Trustees in 1968. Subsequent to this action, the primary responsibility of the Committee became that of overseeing amendments to the Charter of 1968.
Scope and Content
These records of the Committee of Fifteen date from 1965 to 1972 and consist of minutes, agenda, memoranda, correspondence, reports, proposals, clippings, and other documents. Most of the records date from 1970 to 1972 and pertain to the process of amending the Legislative and Judicial Charter of 1968. Of note is the transcript of an open meeting held on March 8, 1971 which was considering two specific amendments. Issues addressed in the earlier records include the closing of the Union Residence, the liquor problem on campus, social regulations, the advising process, and student representation on other university committees.
The bulk of these records appear to have been maintained by Prof. Frederick W. Crawford, chair of the Committee from February 1971 to May 1972.
Access Terms
Crawford, Frederick W.; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Administration.;; College discipline--California--Stanford.; Students--Legal status, laws, etc.--California--Stanford.
Collection Contents
- Committee Minutes and Records, 1965-1972; Series 1
  - Minutes, 1965-66 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1971 Feb. - June (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Open meeting, 8 Mar. 1971: transcript [document is incorrectly dated Mar. 9, 1971] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Open meeting, 8 Mar. 1971: report and statements (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Open meeting, 8 Mar. 1971: summary of oral testimony (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Open meeting, 8 Mar. 1971: text of statement by L. Kedes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Open meeting, 8 Mar. 1971: notes by F. W. Crawford (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1971 Oct. - 1972 April (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1972 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Subcommittee on Student Membership on University Committees, report, May 31, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subcommittee on Judicial Procedure, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Subcommittee on Alternative Systems, 1971-72 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Subcommittee on Individual Rights, 1971-72 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subcommittee on Residual Authority, 1971-72 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Committee of Fifteen rules, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Recommended Committee of Fifteen Amendment Procedure, circa 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Attendance records and notes by F. W. Crawford (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Member lists and appointment records, 1970-72 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Memoranda and Correspondence, 1965-1972; Series 2
  - Memos and correspondence, 1965-66 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda to the committee, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda to the committee, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda to the committee, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Memoranda to the committee from F. W. Crawford, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Memo (not circulated) on Judicial Reform, 5 Apr. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda from F. W. Crawford to others, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda from F. W. Crawford to others, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence to F. W. Crawford concerning C-15 matters, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Memoranda of other university officials concerning C-15 matters, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Memoranda of other university officials concerning C-15 matters, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Memoranda of other university officials concerning C-15 matters, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Documents, 1965-72; Series 3
  - Recommendations of the Committee on Judicial Procedures, 16 Apr. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - ASSU. Recommended changes in by-laws and judicial procedures, 29 Sept. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Union Residence issue, Oct. - Nov., 1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Feldman, Gary. "Thoughts on the Committee of Fifteen,", 11 Nov. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Wilbur Hall System, Dec. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Role of Students in University Governance" [possibly written by Law School professor], circa 1965 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - LASSU. Open House Policy, Jan. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The Stanford Liquor Policy; a Recommendation to President Sterling from the Committee on Student Affairs and Services, 9 Feb. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Rules of the Stanford Judicial Council, [1969] (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Legislative and Judicial Charter of 1968, as amended winter Quarter 1968-69 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Recommendations of SJC in Statement to Stanford Community, June 1969 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Proposed Alterations in Judicial Charter in Section II, with memo from Jack Friedenthal, Aug. 4, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Proposed Amendments to The Legislative and Judicial Charter of 1968, with cover note by Jack H. Friedenthal, circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Status of Proposed Amendments to the Legislative and Judicial Charter of 1968, as of, May 26, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - The Stanford Legislative and Judicial System, issued by the Office of the President, Sept. 25, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Rules of the Stanford Judicial Council, October 1970 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Academic Council, Committee on Committees, report on "community self-discipline,", Nov. 19, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - AAUP, Stanford Chapter. Report on Faculty Self-Discipline, Jan. 1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Rules of the Stanford Judicial Council, draft, Jan. 5, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - ASSU. Resolution on the S.J.C. and Student Self-Discipline, Feb. 1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rules of the Stanford Judicial Council, as amended, May 11, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Proposed Amendments to The Legislative and Judicial Charter of 1968 [Article II E, F, G], proposed by the Committee of Fifteen, - draft and finished document, June 2, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Stanford Legislative and Judicial System, issued by the Office of the President, Sept. 24, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Procedures for the Adjudication of Student Disciplinary Cases Effective, November 29, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Legislative and Judicial Charter of 1968, as amended winter Quarter 1968-69, with further amendments proposed in 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - ASSU. Resolution that C-15 postpone business, circa 1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Telephone call from Kim McCall [transcript], Feb. 10, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Some Issues of Judicial Charter Reform, 29 March 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Amendments relating to the SJC (as of, 17 May 1972) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Possible Amendment Procedures, various drafts, 19 May 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Proposed Charter Amendments, 24 May 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Amended Version of The Legislative and Judicial Charter of 1968 proposed by the Committee of Fifteen, 25-26 May 1972 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Majority Comments on the Amendments to The Legislative and Judicial Charter of 1968 proposed by the Committee of Fifteen, 25-26 May 1972 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Minority Report of C-15, 1971-72, June 1, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - A New Proposal for a Student Judicial System at Stanford, S. Feferman, [Oct. or Nov. 1972] (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - ASSU. Committee for a Stanford Judicial System. Proposal for Establishing a University Judicial System, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Some Major Rights and Responsibilities of Students at Stanford including Rules of Student Conduct, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Miscellaneous Records, Series 4
  - Clippings, 1969 and undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, with related memos and drafts of responses, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, with related memos and drafts of responses, Jan. - Mar. 1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, with related memos and drafts of responses, Apr. - May 1972 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Sources on other university disciplinary systems (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Documents on the history of legislative and judicial procedures at Stanford (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 27)